I thought a pile of dirty rags was moving,
我還以為是地上有破布在動
but it's just that ninja from before.
這不是那時候的忍者嗎？
You look like hell. Someone do you in?
看起來還真狼狽 是幹掉你的好時機囉？
Woah! I want to exchange blows in that state…
都已經傷重到這個程度，還能跟我打
You're really exceptional, aren't you?
你果然不是泛泛之輩
It'll be a challenge to take him out without hurting myself.
現在很難毫髮無傷地打倒他
Your exhaustion is worse than you realize. Your defenses are slow.
你的疲憊已經超出你的認知 防禦動作很慢
Speak for yourself, your center of gravity is off.
我可不這麼認為 你身體的重心偏掉了吧？
You're not used to injuries… I can tell by the way you stand.
你不習慣受傷的左側 從站姿就能看出來了
Your left arm is injured, and you can't use it, right?
你的左手重傷到根本不能用吧？
Okay, that's enough.
好了，到此為止
Please stop your useless posturing.
你們這種較量根本沒有用
It's not useless! A fight begins by predicting the opponent's movements.
才不是沒有用 這是在較量解讀對手的預備動作
It is useless.
沒有用
It's unscientific and unnecessary in the moment. It's pointless.
這種事又不科學 而且眼下這種事根本不重要
What we should be doing now is collecting information.
當務之急是蒐集情報
We must ask him about his experiences so far, where his designated Asaemon is, and…
我們必須問出他至今為止的經歷 負責他的淺衛門下落以及…
who that girl is behind him.
他身後的少女是誰
Fighting won't yield any useful information.
打上一場也得不到任何有用的情報
So…
所以…
We must steal it without killing him.
必須在不殺他的前提下取得情報
Or something like that.
就這麼辦吧
I do know how to keep someone from dying.
我知道不少讓人死不了的辦法
Oh? Do you intend to fight?
喔，你想打嗎？
It will be against the two of us.
一打二嗎？
Now's the time to move… But…
現在就該動手了嗎？不過…
These two are strong. Undeniably strong.
這兩個人很強，無可否認的強
What I've been doing isn't going to work.
我慣用的方式這回行不通
Because I'm not Gabimaru the Hollow anymore.
因為我再也不是伽藍的畫眉丸
What are you doing?
你這是做什麼？
Your strength is promising, so I have a proposal.
你們的實力大有可為 因此我有個提議
Why don't we work together?
要不要跟我合作？
You didn't move.
確實一動也沒動
It would seem that you don't intend to deceive us.
看來你無意欺騙我們
But I'm disappointed.
不過我很失望
I am looking for strong fighters.
我要找的是箇中好手
Not cowards who readily lower their heads to their enemies.
而不是輕易向敵人低頭的膽小鬼
Your thinking is too simplistic.
你真是目光如豆
I want to hear why he would go to these lengths.
我倒想聽聽他為什麼願意這麼做
A monster named "Lord Tensen"?!
叫什麼“天仙大人”的 那個是妖怪嗎？
-I never saw anything so strong! Why not?! -No idea.
-我還沒見到那麼強的，為什麼？ -不知道
More importantly… Regenerative abilities? Not dying after breaking its neck?
而且還有再生能力？ 脖子斷了都不會死？
-What about its organs? Did you see? -Seriously, no idea.
-那內臟呢？你看到了嗎？ -說真的，我不知道
I don't know much.
我哪知道那麼多？
I only want to be pardoned and go back to someone.
我只想得到赦免，回到某個人身邊去
I won't be picky about how I do that.
只要能達到目的，我可以不擇手段
Please lend me your strength.
請兩位助我一臂之力
But… There's no proof that what you're saying is true.
不過，又沒有證據能證明你所言不假
Okay! I'm in!
好，我答應
If I can see both Tensen and Horai, that's killing two birds with one stone.
要是能找到“天仙”或“蓬萊” 那也算得上是一石二鳥了
We were completely lost anyway, right?
反正我們現在也迷路了，不是嗎？
Yes, but… He's a competitor…
是沒錯啦，不過他是競爭對手耶
That's fine. Especially since being pardoned isn't actually my goal.
沒關係，反正呢 我真正的目的也不在赦免
-Didn't you want to sharpen your skills? -That's a means to an end.
-難道是為了磨練劍技嗎？ -那只是其中一種手段
I want immortality.
我要的是不老不死
You mean you're going to use the elixir on yourself?
難道你打算自己服用仙藥嗎？
Of course not! Immortality in itself sounds boring.
當然不是 不老不死表面聽起來就很無聊
I strive to achieve fame and greatness!
我要竭力留下名聲遠播的豐功偉業！
Then my name will be spoken of across the world, and I will become legend.
讓全世界的人都會談論我的名字 我就會成為一代傳奇
The name Gamiya Gantestusai will never age and never die!
我民谷嚴鐵齋之名就會不老不死了
Who I am now, how I look, my words…
我現在是什麼人 長什麼樣，甚至是我說的話
Maintained in pictures and stories,
都會成為圖畫和故事
to be passed down for future lost generations.
代代相傳到無法想像的未來
This is true immortality!
這才是真正的不老不死！
Really… You're the one who's lost.
說真的，你想得還真遠
Whatever. I'm serious.
隨便你說，我可是認真的
So? What are you going to do, Whatever-your-name-is?
怎樣？你打算怎麼辦，某某衛門？
-I've made up my mind. -It's Asaemon.
-我已經下定決心了 -是淺衛門
I'm not interested in exaggerated romantic notions.
我對癡心妄想的浪漫情懷不感興趣
I am very intrigued by the biology of immortal beings.
倒是對不死的生物生理很感興趣
Allow me to eliminate this Tensen person.
請讓我收拾那個叫天仙的傢伙
When you kill him, please let me dissect him!
你解決他之後，一定要讓我解剖喔
We're united.
那麼就一起合作
Well then, please share any other information.
那麼先來分享彼此的情報吧
Yeah. Starting with this girl.
好，先從那個少女開始說起
-Why are you surprised? -Ah, well…
-幹嘛這麼驚訝？ -因為…
She was a little girl just a minute ago, but she grew up.
剛才她還是個小女孩 轉瞬之間她就長大了
Who cares about that? It's just one of the mysteries of women.
誰在乎這種事啊？ 女性的發育本來就很神秘
That's not the problem.
問題不在這裡
Ga… Ga… bi… maru.
畫…畫…眉…丸
You can talk now?
妳會說話了？
What are you?
妳到底是什麼人？
No… More importantly, tell me about the elixir!
不對，先說最重要的 告訴我關於仙藥的事！
I'm sorry.
對不起
Thank you for saving me.
謝謝妳救我一命
If you can talk, please tell me.
既然妳能說話了，請告訴我
Your strange power…
妳那股奇異的力量…
Are you like Lord Tensen?
妳跟天仙大人是同類嗎？
No matter how you look at it, it's strange.
不管怎麼想都很奇怪呢
Senta-dono?
仙汰閣下
You said that Lord Tensen is a god that sorts people's souls in Horai.
你說過天仙大人 是在蓬萊挑選人類靈魂的神吧？
Yes.
對
After everything I've heard, I've come to a conclusion.
聽過這些東西之後，我已有了結論
It is actually impossible for this to be the "real Shinsenkyo."
事實上，這裡絕對不可能 是真正的神仙鄉
This is clearly a religion designed by humans.
這顯然就是人為的宗教體系
-What do you mean? -Horai, Eishu, sitting in prayer.
-什麼意思？ -“蓬萊”、“瀛洲”、“打坐”
And the name "Lord Tensen."
還有“天仙大人”這個名字
These are all originally words used in other religions.
這些原本都是其他宗教的名字
It's a mysterious island. Who cares if its religion is a jumble?
反正這就是座神秘的島 誰管它是混合宗教啊？
Therein lies the problem!
那就是問題所在！
Each of the elements mixed in are one-sided interpretations
每個混合元素都是特定文化圈
from specific cultural spheres.
單方面詮釋的
-Now I've done it… -It means that human religions came first.
-他激動起來了… -首先這就表示這是人為的宗教
The way they're mixed is haphazard, too.
混合的方式也很隨意粗淺
Specific eras and cultures have been mixed only on a superficial level.
只是將特定年代與文化進行表面結合
This crookedness… It feels familiar!
這種不自然的感覺…並不陌生！
-What? What is it? -Moro Makiya!
-幹嘛？怎麼了？ -茂籠木耶！
He founded a religious sect scheming to overthrow the shogun.
他創立了新宗教，並企圖推翻幕府
His religion was very similar to this one.
他所創立的宗教也跟島上宗教雷同
It was cobbled together from various religions with the same crookedness.
都是以各種宗教元素拼湊而成 一樣都很不自然
The defective feeling I had about this place was because of that.
我之所以覺得 這座島像是失敗品，原因就在這裡
Not just the religion, but the monsters and the structure of the island…
不只是宗教，島上的怪物跟結構…
It was all created by someone.
恐怕是某個人創造了這座島
I'm guessing here, but it wasn't just that no one returned from the island…
我推測，登島者不是沒有人回來
It was also that only those turned into flowers returned.
而是只能花化之後回來
Everything was by design from the start.
自始自終都是有人精心策畫
But! No… Because of that!
但是，不對…應該說正因如此！
If this is all by somebody's design, that means it could also be our first clue!
這一切都是出自某人之手的話 就表示有線索可以查清楚了
It also means we should be able to find the elixir and a way out!
也就是說，一定能找到仙藥跟出路！
I'm sorry for blabbering on!
對…對不起，我話太多了！
-No, it's totally fine. -I knew you'd figure it out, Senta-dono.
-是沒關係啦 -不愧是仙汰閣下，果然很了解
You must like this kind of thing.
你一定很喜歡宗教學吧？
Ah, w… well, perhaps…
呃…應該吧…
We can really count on you. Except to take watch.
你真是可靠呢，除了監視以外
If your theory is true, we're in trouble.
如果你的推論正確
A thousand-year-old scheme…
這樣持續千年以上的策劃
I wonder if we three can actually accomplish anything.
我懷疑光靠我們三個 能有辦法應付嗎？
For all we know, Gabimaru and the others are long dead.
據目前所知 畫眉丸跟其他人可能早就死了
No, I'm sure he's alive.
不會，那個人一定還活著
And I'm sure he hasn't given up.
只要活著，他一定還沒有放棄
He's likely out there somewhere with some kind of plan.
很可能現在他也在某處想辦法
So that he can return to the person he misses.
為了能夠見到他心愛的人
That is the type of man Gabimaru is.
畫眉丸就是這種人
If you know Lord Tensen's secrets, or how best to fight him,
如果妳知道天仙大人的秘密 或是打敗他的方法
please tell me.
拜託告訴我
If there's some power I can use to fight Lord Tensen,
如果有我能用來對抗天仙大人的力量
please tell me.
請妳告訴我
-Tao. -Tao?
-道 -道？
Is that what you call power?
妳是這樣稱呼那種力量的？
Tao… Strong… Weak…
道…強大…弱小…
Mind… Body… Strong… Weak…
心智…身體…強大…弱小…
Tanden…
丹田…
Combine…
混合…
Strong… Weak…
強大…弱小…
Scared?
害怕？
-Tao… Strong… Weak… -I don't understand at all.
-道…強大…弱小… -我完全聽不懂
"Tanden"… I think we call that the navel in martial arts.
“丹田”的話 是習武所指的肚臍嗎？
Strictly speaking it's just under the navel.
嚴格說來，是肚臍下面一點的位置
In Chinese medicine it represents a meridian for life energy.
是中國醫學中的經脈觀念
So, what is "Tao" then?
那“道”是什麼？
I don't know.
我不知道
Tao is the energy that flows through all things.
所謂的道，是於萬物中流動的能量
The energy that flows through all things?
於萬物中流動的能量？
Does Lord Tensen control it?
天仙大人控制那股力量嗎？
They do.
沒錯
Everything in this world is created by the transmigration of Tao.
世上的一切都是由道的流轉而成
To feel Tao is to feel the origins of all things in nature.
涉入道即是感受世間萬物的起源
I don't get it.
聽不懂
That's because it's from a particular religious belief.
那畢竟是源自特定宗教信仰的東西
I suppose it must difficult to explain it in a way that we could understand.
我想也很難讓他 用我們聽得懂的方式來解釋
Isn't there some hot teacher out there
有沒有哪個擅長解說
who would be good at explaining it to us?
又帥氣的師父可以解釋給我們聽呢？
If you do things like that, I'll never want to train you.
妳這麼做，我也不會想教妳劍術
I'm begging you, Master! Please teach me how to use a sword!
拜託你，師父，教我用劍吧！
You promised, remember!
你發過誓了，記得嗎？
You promised we'd avenge Tenza together!
你答應我要一起替典坐報仇！
It's no good.
不行
I don't want to watch any more young lives be lost.
我再也不想目睹年輕的生命消逝了
I will fight alone.
我會自己一個人去戰鬥
I will avenge him, but I don't intend to wait for you to improve.
我會替他報仇，但我沒時間等妳進步
I want to fight too! Master!
我也要戰鬥，師父！
As I said, I'm not your master.
我說過了，我不是妳師父
-I haven't taught you anything. -I'm still calling you Master!
-我沒教妳任何東西 -就是這樣才要叫你師父！
You aren't just anyone.
你不是尋常人
When I attacked you from behind… You can't just say that was intuition!
從背後偷襲你都能擋下 那不是直覺能解釋的！
Please…
求求你…
Please teach me too…
求求你也教教我吧…
I don't want to watch any more people I love die…
我再也不想看到心愛的人死掉…
I can't take it anymore!
我再也受不了了！
Please…
求求你…
be my master…
當我的師父…
I can't teach you that kind of intuition in one lesson.
這種直覺力無法用三言兩語解釋清楚
It's too complicated.
這太深奧了
Everything in the world has its own characteristic waves.
這世上所有一切都有特定的波動
-Waves? -Yes.
-波動？ -對
Waves that course around our bodies.
圍繞著身體流動的波動
I can perceive them.
我可以察覺這些波動
It's how I know how tall and heavy you are, and even that your hair is tied up.
因此我能知道妳的身高體重 甚至妳頭髮是束起來的
-Are you telling the truth? -Of course.
-你說的都是真的？ -當然
Using the waves
透過波動
not only gives you intuition, but also physical abilities.
不只能賦予妳感知，還能提升體能
If you reach the peak of Tao,
只要能將道修練至極致
you will attain the power and body of a god.
就能得到如神一般的身體跟力量
In order to harness perception, you must put your mind in order.
想要駕馭覺知，就必須整頓思緒
It can neither be too tempestuous, nor too calm.
不能過於激動，也不能過於平靜
Tao… Mind… Strong… Weak…
道…心智…強大…弱小…
Stillness and movement… Yin and Yang…That cycle…
靜與動，陰與陽，如此循環不止
That transmigration is the key to drawing out Tao.
就是引出道之力的關鍵
In between anger and calm,
讓自己保持在憤怒跟平靜的中間點
or in their coexistence.
或者與兩者並存
You have must assume such a state within your mind.
必須讓自己的心境保持在這種狀態
Once you can do that, it's easier to sense the waves.
這樣一來，就更容易感受到波動
In Buddhism, they call it the Middle Path.
以佛學來說，就是所謂的中庸之道
That mindset can draw out your latent abilities.
這種心境能夠激發出超越自身的能力
For example,
比如說
dodging a power greater than yours,
躲過比自己還強大的力量
or receiving a mortal wound and surviving.
或者受到致命傷卻能存活
But this is not something you master quickly.
但這不是一朝一夕能掌握的能力
To start with, there are many things even I don't know.
連我都還有很多不懂的地方
-In that case, we could start with sword-- -You have to go back to basics.
-既然這樣，就先教我劍… -妳必須從基礎開始
Your stance is terrible.
妳的站姿有問題
What? Then how should I stand?
什麼？那不然我要怎麼站？
First, your left hand should go on the meridian line.
首先左手應該維持在身體中線上
Your right shoulder and foot should face the same way.
右肩與右腳要面對相同方向
Your grip should only be tight when attacking.
只有攻擊的那瞬間才需要握緊刀劍
Any other time, hold it lightly.
其他時候只需輕握就好
-Don't wave it around recklessly. -Huh?
-不要貿然揮劍 -奇怪了
-Focus on the grip of your left hand. -He's teaching me?
-專注於妳左手的握法 -這是在教我嗎？
Just out of habit? Or on purpose?
是習慣使然？還是是故意的？
Killing is forbidden.
嚴禁殺生
-All lives are precious! -Master!
-所有的生命都很寶貴… -師父！
The speed of your sword is important.
劍速很重要
Don't let it soak in blood. The blade will last longer.
不要讓刀身浸滿血水 就能讓刀的壽命更持久
All of these creatures have their own characteristic waves.
這些生物都有各自特定的波動
I can perceive them.
我可以感受得到
Don't rely on your arm strength. Use the weight of your sword.
不要單靠臂力，善用刀身的重量
It's less tiring.
這樣就不易疲憊
Twist the hips at the end only.
最後一個動作才轉腰
Bend your knees and stand tall.
屈膝，然後抬頭挺胸
I can't be your teacher.
我無法成為妳的師父
In my position, it would be inappropriate.
以我的立場而言，這並不合適
However, if you want to learn, you should do so.
但妳想學的話，就自己看著學吧
Yes, Master!
是，師父！
But you won't be a match for that monster.
即使如此，妳也不是那個怪物的對手
You need to drill strikes, but…
技巧仍有待精進，不過…
This island won't allow time for that.
在這座島可沒有時間做那種事
For goodness' sake. Can't even have a conversation here.
真是的，連好好說話的時間都沒有
So if this "Tao" could be a way to kill Lord Tensen…
就算那個“道”可以殺掉天仙大人
It's not like we can take time to learn the basics.
我們可沒有時間慢慢練根基
We'll have to learn how to fight them through battles!
只能從實戰中學習怎麼跟他們戰鬥！
We've got the perfect sparring buddies!
幸好可以拿來練習的對象不少呢！
Now! Teach us how to use this Tao power, little lady!
來吧，小姐 教我們怎麼使用道的力量！
Honestly. What an ill-mannered man.
受不了，真是舉止粗暴的大叔
What's with…
那傢伙…
that one?
是什麼東西？
If you throw a human in a hole,
那是把人類丟到洞裡
it will eventually combine with flowers. That's the idea.
最後就會跟花結合的機制
You developed something amazing, Mu Dan.
你真是發明了很棒的東西呢，牡丹
Now we can make really effective elixirs.
以後收集丹就能更有效率
Make sure you don't kill the human before you put it the hole.
把人丟進洞裡之前 小心別把人給殺掉了
What if it tries to climb out?
要是人類自己爬出來怎麼辦？
If you weaken it enough, the pit will be too deep for a human to escape.
只要讓人類足夠衰弱 洞的深度足以讓衰弱者爬不出來
Plus… The inner defenses will hold it back.
而且洞壁的防禦也會阻撓
They all love to invite others to join them.
他們都想讓別人 落到跟他們一樣的下場
Once they get a hold, they don't let go.
有機會抓到東西就不會放手
That was not an enemy we could take down by force.
那不是光靠蠻力就能擊敗的敵人
We need to assess the situation.
我們必須釐清狀況才行
B… Brother?
哥…
Those assholes… We're going to kill them, Toma.
那群混蛋…我們要幹掉他們，桐馬
-We need to get off the island and tend-- -We're going to kill them, Toma.
-我們必須離開這座島，然後… -我們要幹掉他們，桐馬
-B… but--
-可…可是…
Okay…
好…
-Then let's make a plan. -We don't need a plan.
-那先擬定對策吧 -不用什麼對策
But how…
但那要怎麼…
Generally, those creatures' bottom halves are their weakness.
那些怪物普遍弱點在下半身
When I slashed that monster in half,
我把他劈成兩半時
he regenerated from his upper body.
他是從下半身再生
Not from his head or his heart.
而非從頭或心臟再生
So that means the center of his body is the groin or the navel.
那就表示他身體的中心是腹部或肚臍
He seemed kind of plant-like.
那怪物看來好像某種植物
I wouldn't be surprised if his lower half is his weakness, like roots.
這樣的話，弱點在根部也不令人意外
Impressive as always.
真不愧是哥哥
He sorted the situation and made a plan.
很快就分析出狀況並想好對策
-What? -Nothing.
-怎麼了？ -沒什麼
I was just digesting.
我只是在消化
Digesting what? Oh, right.
消化什麼？我懂了
You want to try it now too? Monster meat.
你也想嚐嚐怪物的肉？
No! And they're not monsters--
才不是，而且他們不是怪物…
You should have some. We need to get back our strength.
你最好吃一點，要恢復體力才行
-Brother! -Oh, so you were still alive.
-哥… -果然還活著啊
Pardon me. My apologies for the sudden interruption.
失禮了，抱歉突然打擾二位
Please do not be alarmed.
兩位無須提防我
-Who are you? -It doesn't matter.
-你是什麼… -那不重要
It's a monster. We'll kill it.
他是怪物，殺了他
No. I have intelligence.
不是，我有智慧的
Let's talk. I am only here for reconnaissance…
我們談談吧，我只是前來偵察而已
On Lord Tensen's orders.
奉天仙大人之命
Is Lord Tensen that guy who was also a girl?
天仙大人是那個不男不女的傢伙？
Indeed. Our master.
正是，那是我們的師尊
You, as well as the other humans who arrived on the island,
除了你們之外，還有其他登島的人類
are currently being scouted by my comrades.
我的同伴也去偵察他們了
We are Doshi.
我們都是道士
Doshi?
道士？
That monster said something about Soshin…
那個怪物提到什麼竈神的…
That is a grave misunderstanding.
那真是誤會大了
Soshin are worthless beings that lack intelligence.
竈神是缺乏智慧的無用生物
They are trash, not even permitted to enter Horai.
是連進蓬萊的資格都沒有的廢物
We Doshi are the personal disciples to Lord Tensen. Right-hand men.
我們道士是 天仙大人的直屬門徒、左右手
Within the castle, we learn from, take care of,
在城內侍奉天仙大人 照料大人的起居
and do troublesome tasks for Lord Tensen.
以及打理大人的麻煩事
That is our job.
那就是我們的職責所在
Horai… Inside the castle…
蓬萊…城內…
Therefore, I must make a request.
因此拜託兩位
Please quietly return to the pit and become Tan.
請乖乖回到洞裡去變成丹吧
Barbarian!
野蠻！
Brother!
哥！
What… is this strength?
這種力量…是什麼？
-You are beyond human. Perhaps Tao is-- -Shut up.
-你實力超乎常人，莫非道已經… -少廢話！
If you are some friend of this Lord Tensen,
既然你是那個什麼天仙大人的同夥
beating you up is the shortest distance to get to those guys.
打倒你就是找到那些傢伙的最快捷徑
I can't believe how perfect this is.
這簡直再完美不過了
I'll question you with my fists.
我就用拳頭逼問你吧
Very well. If you do not wish to resolve this peacefully.
好吧，既然好言相勸你不聽
We have recourse for such a situation as well.
我們也有辦法能應付
Foolish, sinful humans!
愚不可及、滿身罪孽的人類！
You will soon realize you would have liked it better if you had quietly become Tan.
你們很快就會明白 乖乖變成丹還比較好
-Brother-- -Toma! You kill the small fry.
-哥… -桐馬，小嘍囉通通殺掉
I'm counting on you.
交給你了
Understood.
知道了
Brother, you focus on him!
哥，你儘管專心對付那傢伙！
This man is strong.
這個男人很強
But he is considerably fatigued.
但是他已經筋疲力盡了
Looking at the flow of Tao, it's clear as day.
看道的流動就一目瞭然
Moving like this with such injuries… Astounding.
傷得這麼重還能這樣移動，真驚人
But it is meaningless.
但這只是徒勞
Attacks from someone who can't use Tao are but a trifle.
不會使用道的人的攻擊根本不痛不癢
He has aptitude, but at this level…
雖然他有資質，不過這個程度…
Attacks without using Tao are either ineffective
沒有使用道的攻擊幾乎傷不了我
or I can regenerate quickly.
我也能快速再生修復
Astounding. However…
太驚人了，不過…
He is blind to the disorder of Tao… That's a weakness!
道的紊亂產生了 意識的死角，有機可乘！
Brother!
哥！
Subtitle translation by: Mel Nishi
字幕翻譯：洪貞韻